<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<publist>


<article>
  <author>M. Bozkurt, M. R. Mahani, P. Studer, J.-M. Tang, S. R. Schofield, N. J. Curson, M. E. Flatté, A. Yu. Silov, C. F. Hirjibehedin, C. M. Canali, and P. M. Koenraad</author>

  <title>Magnetic anisotropy of single Mn acceptors in GaAs in an external magnetic field</title>

  <journal>
    <link>http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevB.88.205203</link>
    <name>\prb</name> <volume>88</volume> <page>205203</page>
    <year>2013</year> </journal>

  <pdf>PhysRevB.88.205203.pdf</pdf>

  <abstract>We investigate the effect of an external magnetic field on the physical properties of the acceptor hole states associated with single Mn acceptors placed near the (110) surface of GaAs. Cross-sectional scanning tunneling microscopy images of the acceptor local density of states (LDOS) show that the strongly anisotropic hole wave function is not significantly affected by a magnetic field up to 6 T. These experimental results are supported by theoretical calculations based on a tight-binding model of Mn acceptors in GaAs. For Mn acceptors on the (110) surface and the subsurfaces immediately underneath, we find that an applied magnetic field modifies significantly the magnetic anisotropy landscape. However, the acceptor hole wave function is strongly localized around the Mn and the LDOS is quite independent of the direction of the Mn magnetic moment. On the other hand, for Mn acceptors placed on deeper layers below the surface, the acceptor hole wave function is more delocalized and the corresponding LDOS is much more sensitive on the direction of the Mn magnetic moment. However, the magnetic anisotropy energy for these magnetic impurities is large (up to 15 meV), and a magnetic field of 10 T can hardly change the landscape and rotate the direction of the Mn magnetic moment away from its easy axis. We predict that substantially larger magnetic fields are required to observe a significant field dependence of the tunneling current for impurities located several layers below the GaAs surface.</abstract> </article>


<article>
  <author>J. Wang, J.-M. Tang, A. Larson, G. P. Miller, and K. Pohl</author>

  <title>Sharp organic interface of molecular C$_{60}$ chains and a pentacene derivative SAM on Au(788): A combined STM and DFT study</title>

  <journal>
    <link>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.susc.2013.08.015</link>
    <name>\ss</name> <volume>618</volume> <page>78</page>
    <year>2013</year> </journal>

  <pdf>ss618_78_2013.pdf</pdf>

  <abstract>Controlling the molecular structure of the donor-acceptor interface is essential to overcoming the efficiency bottleneck in organic photovoltaics. We present a study of self-assembled fullerene (C60) molecular chains on perfectly ordered 6,13-dichloropentacene (DCP) monolayers forming on a vicinal Au(788) surface using scanning tunneling microscopy in conjunction with density functional theory calculations. DCP is a novel pentacene derivative optimized for photovoltaic applications. The molecules form a brick-wall patterned centered rectangular lattice with the long axis parallel to the monatomic steps that separate the 3.9 nm wide Au(111) terraces. The strong interaction between the C60 molecules and the gold substrate is well screened by the DCP monolayer. At submonolayer C60 coverage, the fullerene molecules form long parallel chains, 1.1 nm apart, with a rectangular arrangement instead of the expected close-packed configuration along the upper step edges. The perfectly ordered DCP structure is unaffected by the C60 chain formation. The controlled sharp highly-ordered organic interface has the potential to improve the conversion efficiency in organic photovoltaics.</abstract> </article>


<article>
  <author>J.-M. Tang, B. T. Collins, and M. E. Flatté</author>

  <title>Electron spin-phonon interaction symmetries and tunable spin relaxation in silicon and germanium</title>

  <journal>
    <link>http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevB.85.045202</link>
    <name>\prb</name> <volume>85</volume> <page>045202</page>
    <year>2012</year> </journal>

  <pdf>PhysRevB.85.045202.pdf</pdf>

  <vjournal> <name>\VJNST</name> <volume>25</volume> <issue>4</issue>
    <year>2012</year> </vjournal>

  <abstract>Compared with direct-gap semiconductors, the valley degeneracy of silicon and germanium opens up new channels for spin relaxation that counteract the spin degeneracy of the inversion-symmetric system. Here the symmetries of the electron-phonon interaction for silicon and germanium are identified and the resulting spin lifetimes are calculated. Room-temperature spin lifetimes of electrons in silicon are found to be comparable to those in gallium arsenide, however, the spin lifetimes in silicon or germanium can be tuned by reducing the valley degeneracy through strain or quantum confinement. The tunable range is limited to slightly over an order of magnitude by intravalley processes.</abstract> </article>


<article>
  <author>J. Wang, I. Kaur, B. Diaconescu, J.-M. Tang, G. P. Miller, and K. Pohl</author>

  <title>Highly ordered assembly of single-domain dichloropentacene over large areas on vicinal gold surfaces</title>

  <journal>
    <link>http://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/nn102468p</link>
    <name>ACS Nano</name> <volume>5</volume> <page>1792</page>
    <year>2011</year> </journal>

  <pdf>ACSNano.5.1792.pdf</pdf>

  <abstract>Defining pathways to assemble long-range-ordered 2D nanostructures of specifically designed organic molecules is required in order to optimize the performance of organic thin-film electronic devices. We report on the rapid fabrication of a nearly perfect self-assembled monolayer (SAM) composed of a single-domain 6,13-dichloropentacene (DCP) brick-wall pattern on Au(788). Scanning tunneling microscopy (STM) results show the well-ordered DCP SAM extends over hundreds of nanometers. Combining STM results with insights from density functional theory, we propose that a combination of unique intermolecular and molecule-step interactions drives the DCP SAM formation.</abstract> </article>


<article>
  <author>J. K. Garleff, A. P. Wijnheijmer, A. Yu. Silov, J. van Bree, W. Van Roy, J.-M. Tang, M. E. Flatté and P. M. Koenraad</author>

  <title>Enhanced binding energy of manganese acceptors close to the GaAs(110) surface</title>

  <journal>
    <link>http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevB.82.035303</link>
    <name>\prb</name> <volume>82</volume> <page>035303</page>
    <year>2010</year> </journal>

  <pdf>PhysRevB.82.035303.pdf</pdf>

  <abstract>Scanning tunneling spectroscopy was performed at low temperature on buried manganese (Mn) acceptors below the (110) surface of gallium arsenide. The main Mn-induced features consisted of a number of dI/dV peaks in the band gap of the host material. The peaks in the band gap are followed by negative differential conductivity, which can be understood in terms of an energy-filter mechanism. The spectroscopic features detected on the Mn atoms clearly depend on the depth of the addressed acceptor below the surface. Combining the depth dependence of the positions of the Mn-induced peaks and using the energy-filter model to explain the negative resistance qualitatively proves that the binding energy of the hole bound to the Mn atom increases for Mn acceptors closer to the surface.</abstract> </article>


<article>
  <author>C. Çelebi, J. K. Garleff, A. Yu. Silov, A. M. Yakunin, P. M. Koenraad, W. Van Roy, J.-M. Tang and M. E. Flatté</author>

  <title>Surface induced asymmetry of acceptor wave functions</title>

  <journal>
    <link>http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevLett.104.086404</link>
    <name>\prl</name> <volume>104</volume> <page>086404</page>
    <year>2010</year> </journal>

  <pdf>PhysRevLett.104.086404.pdf</pdf>

  <url>
     <link>http://prl.aps.org/covers/104/8</link>
     <name>[PRL cover image]</name> </url>

  <abstract>Measurements of the local density of states of individual
    acceptors in III-V semiconductors show that the symmetry of the
    acceptor states strongly depends on the depth of the atom below a
    (110) surface. Tight-binding calculations performed for a
    uniformly strained bulk material demonstrate that strain induced
    by the surface relaxation is responsible for the observed
    depth-dependent symmetry breaking of acceptor wave functions. As
    this effect is strongest for weakly bound acceptors, it explains
    within a unified approach the commonly observed triangular shapes
    of shallow acceptors and the crosslike shapes of deeply bound
    acceptor states in III-V materials.</abstract> </article>


<article>
  <author>W.-M. Huang, J.-M. Tang, and H.-H. Lin</author>

  <title>Power-law singularity in the local density of states due to the point defect in graphene</title>

  <journal>
    <link>http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevB.80.121404</link>
    <name>\prb</name> <volume>80</volume> <page>121404(R)</page>
    <year>2009</year> </journal>

  <pdf>prb80_121404_2009.pdf</pdf>

  <abstract>Defects in graphene give rise to zero modes that are often
    related to the sharp peak in the local density of states near the
    defect site. Here we solved all zero modes induced by a single
    defect in the finite-size graphene and show that their
    contributions to the local density of states vanish in the
    thermodynamic limit. Instead, lots of resonant states emerge at
    low energies and eventually lead to a power-law singularity in the
    local density of states. Our findings show that the impurity
    problem in graphene should be treated as a collective phenomenon
    rather than a single impurity state.</abstract> </article>


<article>
  <author>J.-M. Tang and M. E. Flatté</author>

  <title>Optical and electrical manipulation of single ion spins in semiconductors</title>

  <journal>
    <link>http://dx.doi.org/10.1117/12.828944</link>
    <name>Proc. SPIE</name> <volume>7398</volume> <page>73980K</page>
    <year>2009</year> </journal>

  <pdf>spie7398_73980K_2009.pdf</pdf>

  <abstract>Single ion spins in semiconductors with sizable spin-orbit
    interaction can be optically or electrically manipulated. The
    highly extended anisotropic wave function of the hole bound to
    each magnetic ion is susceptible to external non-magnetic control
    fields. The spin-orbit coupling between the orbital and spin
    character of the hole permits indirect manipulation and readout of
    the ionic spin state. The spin-spin interaction between the
    magnetic ions is electrically or structurally
    controllable.</abstract> </article>


<article>
  <author>M. E. Flatté, A. De, J.-M. Tang, and C. E. Pryor</author>

  <title>Optoelectronic manipulation of single spins in semiconductors</title>

  <journal>
    <link>http://dx.doi.org/10.1117/12.813807</link>
    <name>Proc. SPIE</name> <volume>7225</volume> <page>722504</page>
    <year>2009</year> </journal>

  <pdf>spie7225_722504_2009.pdf</pdf>

  <abstract>In systems with sizable spin-orbit interaction intense
    optical illumination or an electric field can generate an
    effective "pseudomagnetic field" which replaces a true applied
    magnetic field for the efficient and rapid manipulation of
    spins. The theoretical characteristics of optically-induced spin
    precession in self-assembled quantum dots will be described, along
    with the potential for manipulating spins bound to donors and
    acceptors with electric fields.</abstract> </article>


<article>
  <author>D.-A. Luh, C.-M. Cheng, K.-D. Tsuei and J.-M. Tang</author>

  <title>Atomic-layer-resolved bound states in quantum wells analyzed using a pseudopotential approach</title>

  <journal>
    <link>http://link.aps.org/abstract/PRB/v78/e233406</link>
    <name>\prb</name> <volume>78</volume> <page>233406</page>
    <year>2008</year> </journal>

  <pdf>prb78_233406_2008.pdf</pdf>

  <vjournal> <name>\VJNST</name> <volume>18</volume> <issue>1</issue>
    <year>2009</year> </vjournal>

  <abstract>We observed atomic-layer-resolved surface states and
    quantum-well states using angle-resolved photoelectron
    spectroscopy on atomically flat Ag/Au(111) thin films grown with a
    two-step method. The layer dependence of binding energies of the
    bound states was determined unequivocally for a Ag coverage up to
    17 monolayers. We analyzed both the surface states and the
    quantum-well states using a one-dimensional pseudopotential
    approach. Our results show a fruitful combination of growth
    techniques and theoretical analysis for thin-film
    systems.</abstract> </article>


<article>
  <author>J.-M. Tang and M. E. Flatté</author>

  <title>Magnetic Circular Dichroism from the Impurity Band in III-V Diluted Magnetic Semiconductors</title>

  <journal>
    <link>http://link.aps.org/abstract/PRL/v101/e157203</link>
    <name>\prl</name> <volume>101</volume> <page>157203</page>
    <year>2008</year> </journal>

  <pdf>prl101_157203_2008.pdf</pdf>

  <abstract>The magnetic circular dichroism of III-V diluted magnetic
    semiconductors, calculated within a theoretical framework
    suitable for highly disordered materials, is shown to be dominated
    by optical transitions between the bulk bands and an impurity band
    formed from magnetic dopant states. The real-space Green's
    functions incorporate spatial correlations in the disordered
    conduction band and valence-band electronic structure, and include
    extended and localized states on an equal basis. Our findings
    reconcile unusual trends in the experimental magnetic circular
    dichroism in III-V diluted magnetic semiconductors with the
    antiferromagnetic p-d exchange interaction between a magnetic
    dopant spin and its host.</abstract> </article>


<article>
  <author>J. K. Garleff, C. Çelebi, W. Van Roy, J.-M. Tang and M. E. Flatté, P. M. Koenraad</author>

  <title>Atomically precise impurity identification and modification on the manganese doped GaAs(110) surface with scanning tunneling microscopy</title>

  <journal>
    <link>http://link.aps.org/abstract/PRB/v78/e075313</link>
    <name>\prb</name> <volume>78</volume> <page>075313</page>
    <year>2008</year>
  </journal>

  <pdf>prb78_075313_2008.pdf</pdf>

  <abstract>Cross-sectional scanning tunneling microscopy (STM)
    measurements on molecular beam epitaxy grown Mn doped GaAs(110) at
    5 and 77 K are presented. The enhanced mechanical stability of the
    STM at low temperature allows a detailed study of the electronic
    contrast of Mn atoms in the GaAs(110) surface. According to
    reproducible and distinguishable contrast patterns of single Mn
    atoms, we present statistical evidence for a layer by layer
    identification of Mn atoms embedded in the first few monatomic
    layers of the crystal. A comparison with a bulklike theoretical
    approach reveals a semiquantitative agreement with the
    measurements. Remaining differences between theory and experiment
    indicate the influence of the surface as an important factor to
    understand the contrast of impurities close to the
    surface. Furthermore, we report the injection of transition-metal
    atoms into the surface. Finally, reproducible complexes consisting
    of a surface Mn and an adsorbate atom are found and
    manipulated.</abstract> </article>


<article>
  <author>R. C. Myers, M. H. Mikkelsen, J.-M. Tang, A. C. Gossard, M. E. Flatté and D. D. Awschalom</author>

  <title>Zero-field optical manipulation of magnetic ions in semiconductors</title>

  <journal>
    <link>http://www.nature.com/nmat/journal/v7/n3/abs/nmat2123.html</link>
    <name>Nature Materials</name> <volume>7</volume> <page>203</page>
    <year>2008</year> </journal>

  <url>
     <link>nmat7_203_2008-supp.pdf</link>
     <name>[Supplementary Information]</name> </url>

  <pdf>nmat7_203_2008.pdf</pdf>

  <vjournal> <name>\VJNST</name> <volume>17</volume> <issue>10</issue>
    <year>2008</year> </vjournal>

  <abstract>Controlling and monitoring individual spins is desirable
    for building spin-based devices, as well as implementing quantum
    information processing schemes. As with trapped ions in cold
    gases, magnetic ions trapped on a semiconductor lattice have
    uniform properties and relatively long spin
    lifetimes. Furthermore, diluted magnetic moments in semiconductors
    can be strongly coupled to the surrounding host, permitting
    optical or electrical spin manipulation. Here we describe the
    zero-field optical manipulation of a few hundred manganese ions in
    a single gallium arsenide quantum well. Optically created mobile
    electron spins dynamically generate an energy splitting of the ion
    spins and enable magnetic moment orientation solely by changing
    either photon helicity or energy. These polarized manganese spins
    precess in a transverse field, enabling measurements of the spin
    lifetimes. As the magnetic ion concentration is reduced and the
    manganese spin lifetime increases, coherent optical control and
    readout of single manganese spins in gallium arsenide should be
    possible.</abstract> </article>


<article>
  <author>C. Çelebi, P. M. Koenraad, A. Yu. Silov, W. Van Roy, A. M. Monakhov, J.-M. Tang and M. E. Flatté</author>

  <title>Anisotropic Spatial Structure of Deep Acceptor States in GaAs and GaP</title>

  <journal>
    <link>http://link.aps.org/abstract/PRB/v77/e075328</link>
    <name>\prb</name> <volume>77</volume> <page>075328</page>
    <year>2008</year>
  </journal>

  <pdf>prb77_075328_2008.pdf</pdf>

  <abstract>Cross-sectional scanning tunneling microscopy is used to
    identify the origin of the anisotropic electronic structure of
    acceptor states in III-V semiconductors. The density of states
    introduced by a hole bound to an individual Cd acceptor in GaP is
    spatially mapped at room temperature. Similar to the Mn hole wave
    function in GaAs, we found a highly anisotropic, crosslike shape
    of the hole bound to Cd both at the GaP(110) and the
    GaP(1\bar{1}0) orthogonal cleavage planes. The experimentally
    observed similarity of the symmetry properties of Mn:GaAs to
    Cd:GaP shows that the anisotropic structure of acceptor states in
    zinc-blende III-V compounds is determined by the cubic symmetry of
    the host crystal. Nevertheless, the weak spin-orbit interaction in
    GaP leads to a slight modification of the Cd bound-hole wave
    function relative to that of Mn in GaAs. In addition to the
    anisotropic angular structure of the d-like spherical harmonic of
    the wave function, which dominates the appearance of the hole
    ground state far from the ionic core, the admixture of g-like and
    higher order spherical harmonics is identified at the sides of the
    Cd hole wave function. The experimentally obtained results agree
    with both atomistic tight-binding and envelope-function
    effective-mass theoretical models.</abstract> </article>


<article>
  <author>D.-A. Luh, C.-M. Cheng, C.-T. Tsai, K.-D. Tsuei, and J.-M. Tang</author>

  <title>Transition from disorder to order in thin metallic films studied with angle-resolved photoelectron spectroscopy</title>

  <journal>
    <link>http://link.aps.org/abstract/PRL/v100/e027603</link>
    <name>\prl</name> <volume>100</volume> <page>027603</page>
    <year>2008</year>
  </journal>

  <pdf>prl100_027603_2008.pdf</pdf>

  <url>
    <old>http://www.natureasia.com/asia-materials/highlight.php?id=79</old>
    <link>http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/asiamat.2008.23</link>
    <name>[Nature Asia Materials Highlight]</name> </url>
  
  <vjournal> <name>\VJNST</name> <volume>17</volume> <issue>4</issue>
    <year>2008</year> </vjournal>

  <abstract>The transition from disorder to order in Ag film grown on
    Au(111) was investigated by monitoring the quantum well states
    using angle-resolved photoelectron spectroscopy. Our results show
    that the binding energies do not alter, but the in-plane
    dispersion alters from flat to parabolic when the film is
    annealed. We suggest that there are isolated and ordered patches
    scattered across the film at an early stage of the transition and
    that atoms inside the patches are fully ordered along the surface
    normal. These ordered patches grow and merge together as the
    annealing temperature increases.</abstract> </article>


<article>
  <author>B. L. Sheu, R. C. Myers, J.-M. Tang, N. Samarth, D. D. Awschalom, P. Schiffer, and M. E. Flatté</author>

  <title>Onset of ferromagnetism in low-doped Ga$_{1-x}$Mn$_{x}$As</title>

  <journal>
    <link>http://link.aps.org/abstract/PRL/v99/e227205</link>
    <name>\prl</name> <volume>99</volume> <page>227205</page>
    <year>2007</year>
  </journal>

  <pdf>prl99_227205_2007.pdf</pdf>

  <vjournal> <name>\VJNST</name> <volume>16</volume> <issue>24</issue>
    <year>2007</year> </vjournal>

  <abstract> We develop a quantitatively predictive theory for
    impurity-band ferromagnetism in the low-doping regime of
    Ga$_{1-x}$Mn$_{x}$As. We compare it with measurements of a series of
    samples whose compositions span the transition from paramagnetic
    insulating to ferromagnetic conducting behavior. The theoretical
    Curie temperatures depend sensitively on the local fluctuations in
    the Mn-hole binding energy, which originate from Mn disorder and
    As antisite defects. The experimentally determined hopping energy
    is an excellent predictor of the Curie temperature, in agreement
    with the theory.</abstract> </article>


<article>
  <author>F. Marczinowski, J. Wiebe, J.-M. Tang, M. E. Flatté, F. Meier, M. Morgenstern, and R. Wiesendanger</author>

  <title>Local electronic structure near Mn acceptors in InAs: surface-induced symmetry breaking and coupling to host states</title>

  <journal>
    <link>http://link.aps.org/abstract/PRL/v99/e157202</link>
    <name>\prl</name> <volume>99</volume> <page>157202</page>
    <year>2007</year>
  </journal>

  <pdf>prl99_157202_2007.pdf</pdf>

  <abstract>We present low-temperature scanning tunneling spectroscopy
    measurements on Mn acceptors in InAs in comparison with
    tight-binding calculations. We find a strong (001)-mirror
    asymmetry of the bound hole wave function close to the (110)
    surface. In addition, multiple acceptor-related peaks are observed
    and are attributed to a spin-orbit splitting of the acceptor
    level. Because of the $p$-$d$ exchange interaction the local density
    of states near the acceptors is enhanced in the valence band and
    suppressed in the conduction band. We also observe signs of
    anisotropic scattering of the conduction band states by neutral
    acceptors.</abstract> </article>


<article>
  <author>A. M. Yakunin, A. Yu. Silov, P. M. Koenraad, J.-M. Tang, M. E. Flatté, J.-L. Primus, W. Van Roy, J. De Boeck, A. M. Monakhov, K. S. Romanov, I. E. Panaiotti, and N. S. Averkiev</author>

  <title>Warping a single Mn acceptor wavefunction by straining the GaAs host</title>

  <journal>
    <link>http://www.nature.com/nmat/journal/v6/n7/abs/nmat1936.html</link>
    <name>Nature Materials</name> <volume>6</volume> <page>512</page>
    <year>2007</year> </journal>

  <pdf>nmat6_512_2007.pdf</pdf>

  <url>
     <link>nmat6_512_2007-news.pdf</link>
     <name>[News and Views]</name> </url>
  <url>
     <link>nmat6_512_2007-supp.pdf</link>
     <name>[Supplementary Information]</name> </url>

  <vjournal> <name>\VJNST</name> <volume>16</volume> <issue>4</issue>
    <year>2007</year> </vjournal>

  <abstract>Transition-metal dopants such as Mn determine the
    ferromagnetism in dilute magnetic semiconductors such as
    Ga$_{1-x}$Mn$_{x}$As.  Recently, the acceptor states of Mn dopants
    in GaAs were found to be highly anisotropic owing to the symmetry
    of the host crystal.  Here, we show how the shape of such a state
    can be modified by local strain. The Mn acceptors near InAs
    quantum dots are mapped at room temperature by scanning tunnelling
    microscopy. Dramatic distortions and a reduction in the symmetry
    of the wavefunction of the hole bound to the Mn acceptor are
    observed originating from strain induced by quantum dots.
    Calculations of the acceptor-state wavefunction in the presence of
    strain, within a tight-binding model and within an effective-mass
    model, agree with the experimentally observed shape. The magnetic
    easy axes of strained lightly doped Ga$_{1-x}$Mn$_{x}$As can be
    explained on the basis of the observed local density of states for
    the single Mn spin.</abstract> </article>


<article>
  <author>D. Kitchen, A. Richardella, P. Roushan, J.-M. Tang, M. E. Flatté, and A. Yazdani</author>

  <title>Hole-mediated interactions of Mn pairs on GaAs (110)</title>

  <journal>
    <link>http://link.aip.org/link/?JAP/101/09G515</link>
    <name>\jap</name> <volume>101</volume> <page>09G515</page>
    <year>2007</year> </journal>

  <pdf>jap101_09G515_2007.pdf</pdf>

  <abstract>An STM-substitution technique is used to incorporate
    single Mn atoms into Ga sites in GaAs (110) surfaces. The
    electronic states near a single Mn in the acceptor configuration
    produce a strong in-gap resonance associated with the acceptor
    level. The isolated Mn acceptor is probed in both $p$-type and
    $n$-type environments to access the neutral and ionized acceptor
    configurations. The Mn acceptor at the surface substitution site
    shares bulk characteristics that compare well with tight-binding
    calculations. The anisotropic structure of the Mn hole state plays
    an important role in hole-mediated interactions between the Mn
    acceptors. Isolated Mn pairs show a strong interaction dependence
    on crystal orientation and spacing. Certain pair orientations
    produce a strong splitting of the acceptor level into two levels
    with bonding-like and anti-bonding-like symmetries. A
    tight-binding model relates the acceptor level splitting and the
    spin-spin interaction energy $J$.</abstract> </article>


<article>
  <author>J.-M. Tang, J. Levy and M. E. Flatté</author>

  <title>All-electrical control of single ion spins in a semiconductor</title>

  <journal>
    <link>http://link.aps.org/abstract/PRL/v97/e106803</link>
    <name>\prl</name> <volume>97</volume> <page>106803</page>
    <year>2006</year> </journal>

  <pdf>prl97_106803_2006.pdf</pdf>

  <vjournal> <name>\VJNST</name> <volume>14</volume> <issue>12</issue>
    <year>2006</year> </vjournal>
  <vjournal> <name>\VJQI</name> <volume>6</volume> <issue>9</issue>
    <year>2006</year> </vjournal>

  <abstract>We propose a method for all-electrical manipulation of
    single ion spins substituted into a semiconductor. Mn ions with a
    bound hole in GaAs form a natural example. Direct electrical
    manipulation of the ion spin is possible, because electric fields
    manipulate the orbital wave function of the hole, and through the
    spin-orbit coupling the spin is reoriented as well. Coupling ion
    spins can be achieved using gates to control the size of the hole
    wave function. Coherent manipulation of ionic spins may find
    applications in high-density storage and in scalable coherent or
    quantum information processing.</abstract> </article>


<article>
  <author>D. Kitchen, A. Richardella, J.-M. Tang, M. E. Flatté, and A. Yazdani</author>

  <title>Atom-by-atom substitution of Mn in GaAs and visualization of their hole-mediated interactions</title>

  <journal>
    <link>http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v442/n7101/abs/nature04971.html</link>
    <name>Nature</name> <volume>442</volume> <page>436</page>
    <year>2006</year> </journal>

  <pdf>nature442_436_2006.pdf</pdf>

  <url>
     <link>http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v442/n7101/index.html</link>
     <name>[Nature cover image]</name> </url>
  <url>
     <link>nature442_436_2006-news.pdf</link>
     <name>[News and Views]</name> </url>
  <url>
     <link>nature442_436_2006-supp.pdf</link>
     <name>[Supplementary Information]</name> </url>

  <vjournal>
    <name>\VJNST</name> <volume>14</volume> <issue>6</issue>
    <year>2006</year> </vjournal>

  <abstract>The discovery of ferromagnetism in Mn-doped GaAs has
    ignited interest in the development of semiconductor technologies
    based on electron spin and has led to several proof-of-concept
    spintronic devices. A major hurdle for realistic applications of
    Ga$_{1-x}$Mn$_{x}$As, or other dilute magnetic semiconductors,
    remains that their ferromagnetic transition temperature is below
    room temperature. Enhancing ferromagnetism in semiconductors
    requires us to understand the mechanisms for interaction between
    magnetic dopants, such as Mn, and identify the circumstances in
    which ferromagnetic interactions are maximized. Here we describe
    an atom-by-atom substitution technique using a scanning tunneling
    microscope (STM) and apply it to perform a controlled study at the
    atomic scale of the interactions between isolated Mn acceptors,
    which are mediated by holes in GaAs. High-resolution STM
    measurements are used to visualize the GaAs electronic states that
    participate in the Mn-Mn interaction and to quantify the
    interaction strengths as a function of relative position and
    orientation. Our experimental findings, which can be explained
    using tight-binding model calculations, reveal a strong dependence
    of ferromagnetic interaction on crystallographic orientation. This
    anisotropic interaction can potentially be exploited by growing
    oriented Ga$_{1-x}$Mn$_{x}$As structures to enhance the
    ferromagnetic transition temperature beyond that achieved in
    randomly doped samples.</abstract> </article>


<article>
  <author>A. M. Yakunin, A. Yu. Silov, P. M. Koenraad, J.-M. Tang, M. E. Flatté, W. Van Roy, J. De Boeck, and J. H. Wolter</author>

  <title>Spatial structure of Mn-Mn acceptor pairs in GaAs</title>

  <journal>
    <link>http://link.aps.org/abstract/PRL/v95/p256402</link>
    <name>\prl</name> <volume>95</volume> <page>256402</page>
    <year>2005</year> </journal>

  <pdf>prl95_256402_2005.pdf</pdf> 

  <vjournal>
    <name>\VJNST</name> <volume>12</volume> <issue>26</issue>
    <year>2005</year> </vjournal>

  <abstract>The local density of states of Mn-Mn pairs in GaAs is
    mapped with cross-sectional scanning tunneling microscopy and
    compared with theoretical calculations based on envelope-function
    and tight-binding models. These measurements and calculations show
    that the crosslike shape of the Mn-acceptor wave function in GaAs
    persists even at very short Mn-Mn spatial separations. The
    resilience of the Mn-acceptor wave function to high doping levels
    suggests that ferromagnetism in GaMnAs is strongly influenced by
    impurity-band formation. The envelope-function and tight-binding
    models predict similarly anisotropic overlaps of the Mn wave
    functions for Mn-Mn pairs. This anisotropy implies differing Curie
    temperatures for Mn-doped layers grown on differently oriented
    substrates.</abstract> </article>


<article>
  <author>J.-M. Tang and M. E. Flatté</author>

  <title>Spin-orientation-dependent spatial structure of a magnetic acceptor state in a zincblende semiconductor</title>

  <journal>
    <link>http://link.aps.org/abstract/PRB/v72/p161315</link>
    <name>\prb</name> <volume>72</volume> <page>161315(R)</page>
    <year>2005</year> </journal>

  <pdf>prb72_161315_2005.pdf</pdf>>

  <abstract>The spin orientation of a magnetic dopant in a zincblende
    semiconductor strongly influences the spatial structure of an
    acceptor state bound to the dopant. The acceptor state has a
    roughly oblate shape with the short axis aligned with the dopant's
    core spin. For a Mn dopant in GaAs the local density of states at
    a site 8 \AA{} away from the dopant can change by 90\% when
    the Mn spin orientation changes.  These changes in the local
    density of states could be probed by scanning tunneling microscopy
    to infer the dopant's spin orientation.</abstract> </article>


<article>
  <author>J.-M. Tang and M. E. Flatté</author>

  <title>Impurity induced low-energy resonances in Bi$_{2}$Sr$_{2}$CaCu$_{2}$O$_{8+\delta}$</title>

  <journal>
    <link>http://publish.aps.org/abstract/PRB/v70/p140510</link>
    <name>\prb</name> <volume>70</volume> <page>140510(R)</page>
    <year>2004</year> </journal>

  <pdf>prb70_140510_2004.pdf</pdf>

  <vjournal>
    <name>\VJAS</name> <volume>7</volume> <issue>9</issue>
    <year>2004</year> </vjournal>

  <abstract>We study sharp low-energy resonance peaks in the local
    density of states (LDOS) induced by Zn impurities or possible Cu
    vacancies in superconducting
    Bi$_{2}$Sr$_{2}$CaCu$_{2}$O$_{8+\delta}$. The measured structure of
    these near-zero-bias resonances is quantitatively reproduced by an
    extended impurity potential without invoking internal impurity
    states or sophisticated tunneling models. The Zn potential extends
    at least to the nearest-neighbor Cu sites, and the range of order
    parameter suppression extends at least 8 \AA{} away from the Zn
    site. We further show that the local spin susceptibilities near Zn
    impurities increase rather than decrease with decreasing
    temperature in the superconducting state due to the sharp increase
    of the LDOS near the Fermi level.</abstract> </article>


<article>
  <author>J.-M. Tang</author>

  <title>Structure of excited vortices with higher angular momentum in Bose-Einstein condensates</title>
  
  <journal>
    <link>http://publish.aps.org/abstract/PRA/v70/p043626</link>
    <name>\pra</name> <volume>70</volume> <page>043626</page>
    <year>2004</year> </journal>
  
  <pdf>pra70_043626_2004.pdf</pdf> 

  <abstract>The structure of vortices in Bose-Einstein condensed
    atomic gases is studied taking into account many-body correlation
    effects.  It is shown that for excited vortices the particle
    density in the vortex core increases as the angular momentum of
    the system increases. The core density can increase by several
    times with only a few percent change in the angular momentum. This
    result provides an explanation for the observations in which the
    measured angular momentum is higher than the estimation based on
    counting the number of vortices and the visibility of the vortex
    cores is simultaneously reduced.  The calculated density profiles
    for the excited vortices are in good agreement with experimental
    measurements of a single vortex.</abstract> </article>


<article>
  <author>A. M. Yakunin, A. Yu. Silov, P. M. Koenraad, W. Van Roy, J. De Boeck, J. H. Wolter, J.-M. Tang and M. E. Flatté</author>

  <title>Spatial structure of an individual Mn acceptor in GaAs</title>

  <journal>
    <link>http://publish.aps.org/abstract/PRL/v92/p216806</link>
    <name>\prl</name> <volume>92</volume> <page>216806</page>
    <year>2004</year> </journal>

  <pdf>prl92_216806_2004.pdf</pdf> 

  <abstract>The wave function of a hole bound to an individual Mn
    acceptor in GaAs is spatially mapped by scanning tunneling
    microscopy at room temperature and an anisotropic, crosslike shape
    is observed. The spatial structure is compared with that from an
    envelope-function, effective mass model and from a tight-binding
    model. This demonstrates that anisotropy arising from the cubic
    symmetry of the GaAs crystal produces the crosslike shape for the
    hole wave function. Thus the coupling between Mn dopants in GaMnAs
    mediated by such holes will be highly anisotropic.</abstract>
    </article>


<article>
  <author>L.-J. Chen, D. J. Thouless, and J.-M. Tang</author>

  <title>Bernstein-Greene-Kruskal solitary waves in three-dimensional magnetized plasma</title>

  <journal>
    <link>http://publish.aps.org/abstract/PRE/v69/p055401</link>
    <name>\pre</name> <volume>69</volume>
    <page>055401(R)</page> <year>2004</year> </journal>

  <pdf>pre69_055401_2004.pdf</pdf> 

  <abstract>We study the width-amplitude relation for
    three-dimensional Bernstein-Greene-Kruskal (BGK) electrostatic
    solitary waves in magnetized plasmas, taking into account the
    dynamics of both electrons and ions. We obtain two coupled
    inequalities that constrain the amplitude and the widths parallel
    and perpendicular to the magnetic field for a Gaussian potential,
    and demonstrate how the solution space is further constrained by
    the finite temperature ratio between electrons and ions. The
    description is valid for both the electron and ion mode solitary
    waves. Our results provide a quantitative basis for understanding
    the ubiquity of BGK waves in widely different classes of
    collisionless plasmas.</abstract> </article>


<article>
  <author>J.-M. Tang and M. E. Flatté</author>

  <title>Multiband tight-binding model of local magnetism in Ga$_{1-x}$Mn$_{x}$As</title>

  <journal>
    <link>http://publish.aps.org/abstract/PRL/v92/p047201</link>
    <name>\prl</name> <volume>92</volume> <page>047201</page>
    <year>2004</year> </journal>

  <pdf>prl92_047201_2004.pdf</pdf>

  <abstract>We present the spin and orbitally resolved local density
    of states (LDOS) for a single Mn impurity and for two nearby Mn
    impurities in GaAs. The GaAs host is described by a $sp$$^{3}$
    tight-binding Hamiltonian, and the Mn impurity is described by a
    local $p$-$d$ hybridization and on-site potential.  Local
    spin-polarized resonances within the valence bands significantly
    enhance the LDOS near the band edge. For two nearby parallel Mn
    moments the acceptor states hybridize and split in energy. Thus
    scanning tunneling spectroscopy can directly measure the Mn-Mn
    interaction as a function of distance.</abstract> </article>


<article>
  <author>J.-M. Tang and M. E. Flatté</author>

  <title>Van Hove features in Bi$_{2}$Sr$_{2}$CaCu$_{2}$O$_{8+\delta}$ and effective parameters for Ni impurities inferred from STM spectra</title>

  <journal>
    <link>http://publish.aps.org/abstract/PRB/v66/p060504</link>
    <name>\prb</name> <volume>66</volume> <page>060504(R)</page>
    <year>2002</year> </journal>

  <pdf>prb66_060504_2002.pdf</pdf>

  <vjournal>
    <name>\VJAS</name> <volume>3</volume> <issue>4</issue>
    <year>2002</year> </vjournal>

  <abstract>We present a detailed quantitative comparison between
    theoretical calculations of the local density of states and recent
    experimental measurements of scanning tunneling spectra around Ni
    impurities in Bi$_{2}$Sr$_{2}$CaCu$_{2}$O$_{8+\delta}$. A double-peak
    structure on the hole side of the spectrum at the Ni site is
    identified as the spin-split Van Hove singularity in the band
    structure. The Ni atom induces local changes in hopping matrix
    elements comparable in size to the induced on-site spin-dependent
    potential. We find evidence from the measurements of
    order-parameter suppression in the vicinity of the Ni impurity.
    These extracted impurity parameters can be of use in quantitative
    calculations of macroscopic response properties, such as the ac
    conductivity.</abstract> </article>


<article>
  <author>J.-M. Tang</author>

  <title>Variational wave functions of a vortex in cyclotron motion</title>

  <journal>
    <link>http://ejournals.wspc.com.sg/ijmpb/15/1510n11/S0217979201006082.html</link>
    <name>\ijmpb</name> <volume>15</volume> <page>1601</page>
    <year>2001</year> </journal>

  <pdf>ijmpb15_1601_2001.pdf</pdf>

  <book>
    <name>Recent Progress in Many-Body Theories</name>
    <editor>R. F. Bishop, K. A. Gernoth, N. R. Walet and Y. Xian</editor>
    <publisher>World Scientific</publisher>
    <address>Singapore</address> <year>2000</year>
    <pages>315-8</pages> </book>

  <abstract>A microscopic theory is presented to provide a basis for
  the intuitive analogy between a quantized vortex in a superfluid and
  an electron in an uniform magnetic field in two dimensions. A
  one-to-one correspondence between the rotational states of a vortex
  in a cylinder and the cyclotron states of an electron in the central
  gauge is found. Like the Landau levels of an electron, the energy
  levels of a vortex are highly degenerate. However, the gap between
  two adjacent energy levels depends not only on the quantized
  circulation, but also increases with the energy, and scales with the
  size of the vortex.</abstract> </article>


<article>
  <author>J.-M. Tang</author>

  <title>The structure of a quantized vortex in a Bose-Einstein condensate</title>

  <journal>
    <link>http://dx.doi.org/10.1023/A:1017516706057</link>
    <name>\jltp</name> <volume>121</volume> <page>287</page>
    <year>2000</year> </journal>

  <pdf>jltp121_287_2000.pdf</pdf>

  <abstract>The structure of a quantized vortex in a Bose-Einstein
    Condensate is investigated using the projection method developed
    by Peierls, Yoccoz, and Thouless. This method was invented to
    describe the collective motion of a many-body system beyond the
    mean-field approximation. The quantum fluctuation has been
    properly built into the variational wave function, and a vortex is
    described by a linear combination of Feynman wave functions
    weighted by a Gaussian distribution in their center positions. In
    contrast to the solution of the Gross-Pitaevskii equation, the
    particle density is finite at the vortex axis and the vorticity is
    distributed in the core region.</abstract> </article>


<article>
  <author>J.-M. Tang and D. J. Thouless</author>

  <title>Longitudinal force on a moving potential</title>

  <journal>
    <link>http://publish.aps.org/abstract/PRB/v58/p14179</link>
    <name>\prb</name> <volume>58</volume> <page>14179</page>
    <year>1998</year> </journal>

  <pdf>prb58_14179_1998.pdf</pdf>

  <abstract>We show a formal result of the longitudinal force acting
    on a moving potential. The potential can be velocity dependent,
    which appears in various interesting physical systems, such as
    electrons in the presence of a magnetic flux line, or phonons
    scattering off a moving vortex. By using the phase-shift analysis,
    we are able to show the equivalence between the adiabatic
    perturbation theory and the kinetic theory for the longitudinal
    force in the dilute gas limit.</abstract> </article>

</publist>
